Muir mss. IV, 1958-1971 LMC 2517
Lilly Library
Muir mss. IV
1958-1971
Lilly Library
Muir, Percy, 1894-1979
LMC 2517
1 Box 1 standard
The Muir mss. IV 1958-1971, consist of correspondence of book and manuscript dealer Percival Horace Muir (1894-1979) and bookseller Elkin Mathews, Ltd. relating specifically to items later acquired by the Lilly Library of Indiana University.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Many collections are housed offsite; retrieval requires advance notice. Please make an appointment a minimum of one week in advance of your visit.
Biographical Note
Percival Horace Muir (1894-1979) began his career as a bookseller in 1920. He joined the London antiquarian booksellers Elkin Mathews in 1930, and would remain there until his death in Norfolk on November 24, 1979. Muir was an influential figure among booksellers and book collectors around the world. As president of the Antiquarian Booksellers Association in Britain from 1945-1947, Muir chaired the first conference of the International League of Antiquarian Booksellers (ILAB) in 1947. He then served as president of the ILAB from 1950 until 1952. At the end of his term in this office, he was elected Life President of Honor.
Arrangement
The collection has two series: Correspondence and Business Papers. Correspondence is arranged chronologically by year and then alphabetically by last name of correspondent.
Scope and Content Note
Correspondence consists of letters between Percy Muir and Elkin Mathews, Ltd. with libraries, book dealers, and collectors. Correspondence is mainly airmail and typescript, one page each. Some of the collectors' letters comprise several pages. The letters are addressed to Elkin Mathews Ltd., Percy Muir, Laurie Deval, or Reg Read. Many are annotated by Percy Muir or staff and some have manuscript additions by their authors. Business Papers include orders and invoices, materials related to advertising, materials related to the International League of Antiquarian Booksellers, and copies of bibliographies from "Book and Magazine Collector."
Related Material
See Muir mss. I, II, III, and V and Elkin Mathews Ltd. mss also located at the Lilly Library, Indiana University, Bloomington, Indiana.
Acquisition Information
Purchase: 2005
Booksellers and bookselling; Muir, Percy, 1894-1979; E. Mathews (Firm); Lilly Library (Indiana University, Bloomington); International League of Antiquarian Booksellers.
- I. CORRESPONDENCE
  - 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - 1960 (Box 1)
  - 1961-1962 (Box 1)
  - 1963 (Box 1)
  - 1964 (Box 1)
  - 1965 (Box 1)
  - 1966 (Box 1)
  - 1967 (Box 1)
  - 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
  - Undated (Box 1)
  - Cagle, William Rea, Librarian, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Coke, Gerald Edward, business executive, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Connolly, Terrence L., 1958-1960 (Box 1)
  - Conway, William E., 1968 (Box 1)
  - Davis, Edna, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Fuld, James Jeffrey, lawyer, musicologist, 1960-1965 (Box 1)
  - Jackson, William A., 1958-1964 (Box 1)
  - Lodge, Constance, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - Mayor, A. Hyatt, 1960-1963 (Box 1)
  - McWilliams, David Jackson, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Morse, Peter, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Person, Carl, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Randall, David, 1965 (Box 1)
  - Spenson, Albert, 1966 (Box 1)
  - Stoddard, Roger E., 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Warren, Virginia, 1959-1968 (Box 1)
- II. BUSINESS PAPERS
  - Orders and invoices, 1963-1968 (Box 1)
  - Advertising, 1968 (Box 1)
  - Material related to the international league of antiquarian booksellers, 1971 (Box 1)
  - Copies of bibliographies from book and magazine collector, undated (Box 1)